On the morning of the 6th of April 1930,
Mahatma Gandhi made his way to this
[music] remote beach.
It was the end of a grueling month-long
march [music] in the fight for
independence.
He knew that the police were waiting for
him because what Gandhi intended to do
[music] next was illegal.
He wanted to provoke India's [music]
British rulers with a simple but
powerful statement, scooping up sea salt
from the beach.
But Indians were forbidden to collect
salt without paying a tax. For Gandhi,
that was little more than theft from the
poor.
This pilgrimage to the sea was a superb
political gesture. It's no exaggeration
to say that the eyes of the world were
watching this beach. No one knew what to
expect. Would he be arrested or his
followers attacked?
As my journey continues, I uncover a
different Gandhi from the saintly
Hollywood version.
I find a man whose rise to power was
>> [music]
>> anything but inevitable.
In these crucial years, Gandhi had to
endure British jails,
insults from opponents and supporters,
and years [music] as a political
irrelevance.
He was almost a footnote in history.
And I discover the radical philosophy
that brought him fame is not as
straightforward as it seems.
>> Truth?
>> Yeah.
>> Non-violence or love?
>> Gandhi is a pacifist, and yet his
campaigns [music]
need violence to succeed. And he's an
outspoken critic of those who die for
his cause.
>> [music]
>> Gandhi came home to India in January
1915 as a stranger.
He'd been away in South Africa for 22
years fighting for the rights of his
fellow Indians.
This London-trained lawyer was now fired
by a belief that he had a god-given
[music]
mission to change India.
At the time, India was part of the
British Empire. Gandhi wanted nothing
less than home rule for his people.
In South Africa, he developed an
effective political tool, a form of
nonviolent protest that he called
Satyagraha.
It means truth force.
By 1914, Gandhi felt that Satyagraha
could bring about change in India.
Gandhi realized that he was out of touch
with his homeland, so he decided to
spend a year traveling in an unknown
world.
>> [music]
>> Then as now, the train was the best way
to see India.
Gandhi decided that he and his wife
Kasturba would travel in third class.
What they found shocked them. The
carriages were overcrowded, the food was
covered in flies, the lavatories were
horrifying, and the tea was undrinkable.
And it wasn't just the trains. As he
crisscrossed the country, Gandhi saw the
rural poverty, what he believed to be
fake Hindu practices, and the corrupting
influence of Western ideas. Clearly,
there would be plenty to occupy him
here.
>> What Gandhi saw on his travels convinced
him that India needed social, but also
profound spiritual change.
It had to earn home rule by becoming a
more morally pure nation.
It was a vision he hoped would be shared
by India's politicians, who knew the
country better than he did.
But his ideas weren't met with much
enthusiasm.
>> Soon after Gandhi arrived back in India,
a number of receptions were laid on for
him by leading political figures. Gandhi
spoke about his beliefs and his aims,
but he was no orator, and his audience,
dressed mostly in European clothes, were
rather embarrassed by this unimpressive
hero from South Africa in traditional
Gujarati clothes.
But Gandhi had a plan to create a
spiritual base to transform society, a
plan that didn't need the snooty
political elite.
>> It was the start [music] of a long,
turbulent journey. There would be
notable triumphs, but surprising
setbacks, too.
Gandhi could be in the thick of it one
moment, leading the struggle for an
India free from colonial rule, and
isolated the next,
languishing in the political wilderness.
It's a miracle that he kept on fighting
at all.
>> [music]
>> Gandhi's quest to shake off the British
Raj began in his home state of Gujarat.
He decided to found an ashram or
religious community that would be at the
heart of his political work and an
inspiration for Indian society.
But he had few followers and not much
money.
This wasn't to be a community set in a
rural idyll. Gandhi chose a location
here in Ahmedabad, one of India's most
industrialized cities. Its many textile
mills had given it the nickname [music]
the Manchester of India.
The ashram was built on waste ground on
the banks of a river just outside
Ahmedabad and soon grew into an
organized community of about 300 people.
Gandhi wanted it to return to the
virtues of simple village life,
especially the spinning and weaving of
cloth that he believed could make
Indians self-sufficient.
Today, the ashram is a museum paying
tribute to its remarkable founder.
>> I don't know when I came here first
because I must have been about a month
old when
>> I've brought back to the ashram Narayan
Desai.
He grew up here in the 1920s with Gandhi
as a friend and inspiration.
Narayan's father, Mahadev Desai, was
Gandhi's secretary and trusted adviser
for over 25 years.
Today, Narayan is one of the few
remaining people who can claim to have
known Mahatma Gandhi.
While a pupil at the ashram school, he
had his own views on Gandhi's
philosophies.
>> My teacher very often came from behind
and just caught hold of my ear and
dragged me like that.
That gave me an opportunity to write a
letter
to Gandhi saying, "Well, this is what is
happening in your ashram. You talk about
non-violence."
>> [laughter]
>> So, you think you think Gandhi told her,
"No more pulling children's ears."
>> Gandhi might have pulled her.
>> Pulled her ear.
>> [laughter]
>> Maybe not literally.
>> No, no.
>> I'll follow you.
Even before the ashram opened, Gandhi
had drawn up rules for the community to
follow.
They're fascinating, encapsulating the
philosophy that would guide him for the
rest of his life.
>> Truth.
>> Yeah.
>> Non-violence or love, chastity,
not stealing,
non-possession or poverty. So, you
should give up your your worldly goods.
Fearlessness. One cannot follow truth or
love so long as one is subject to fear.
So, it was really important for him that
that people should not be afraid of
anything.
>> Yeah.
That was the the revolutionary
part of it, you see.
>> At the heart of the ashram, and opened
especially for us, is Gandhi's room, a
place full of memories for Narayan.
So, this this is where he used to sit.
>> drawing room as well as his study.
>> Do you remember him sitting here?
>> I could more remember my
father sitting over there, taking
dictations, sometimes showing him the uh
papers, etc.
>> How do you feel
when you're in this room?
>> I feel
as if I come back to my old house.
Yeah, because this is something like my
own place.
He was 56 years older than me.
But, there was no distinction of age
between him and me.
You felt as if
he entered your heart
with his book.
>> Looking at the spot where Gandhi used to
sit and receive so many of his guests,
listening to Narayan who essentially
grew up at his feet, it's all brought
alive the story of Gandhi in a way I
didn't expect. For the first time, I
feel I have a better sense of his full
personality, of this human being who
managed to attract so many people to his
cause.
The ashram was soon a place of
pilgrimage.
People came here believing that just a
glimpse of Gandhi would give them a
spiritual blessing.
He began to be called Mahatma, great
soul.
The ashram worked well as a base from
which Gandhi organized politically
unfashionable campaigns supporting
peasant farmers and striking textile
workers.
Gradually his reputation grew as a
champion of the poor.
And events were unfolding back in London
that would transform Gandhi's fortunes.
In the summer of 1918, the British judge
Sir Sydney Rowlatt released a report
into the danger of Indian seditious
behavior.
He recommended that highly unpopular
wartime legislation designed to curb
unrest should be extended into
peacetime.
Gandhi was furious, denouncing it as a
harsh betrayal of India's support for
the war.
>> [music]
>> It made him more determined than ever to
be free from colonial rule.
He prepared for what he called the
greatest battle of my life.
>> When Gandhi heard that the Viceroy had
approved and signed the Rowlatt Act, he
moved decisively while other politicians
dithered. Until now, he had been engaged
in regional campaigns. This was a single
issue on which he could launch a
nationwide nonviolent movement
deliberately opposing British authority
in India. It was the start of a 28-year
struggle.
>> The leaders of the country's largest
political organization, the Indian
National Congress, were lukewarm towards
Gandhi [music] and his political
tactics. They warned him that the
protest would get violent.
But Gandhi trusted the Indian people to
grasp the religious [music] dimension to
Satyagraha.
That they had to be pure in their
motives and even full of love for their
oppressor.
With Congress unwilling to support any
act of disobedience, Gandhi assembled
[music] his own team to coordinate
opposition to the Rowlatt Act.
>> In March 1919, Gandhi called for a
nationwide hartal, a day of protest. All
shops, offices, and businesses were
asked to close. He wrote to the Viceroy
saying the protest would show that
physical force was nothing compared to
moral force, and moral force never
fails.
>> It was a bold statement, but after the
earlier setbacks, the protest would be
the first real test of Gandhi's
leadership and support.
On the streets of Delhi, I met up with
Professor Mridula Mukherjee, who has
studied the campaign of 1919.
I wanted to know just how successful it
was.
>> Remarkably so, almost beyond everybody's
expectations.
It was the first nationwide political
protest in Indian history.
In many cities, there were meetings of
over 100,000 people. So, while
normal activity came to a standstill, it
was not that the streets were deserted.
People were out on the streets, but they
were in political protest.
>> From Gandhi's perspective, was the
hartal successful?
>> I think immensely so, because the notion
that people all over India could get
together with minimal organization
around a moral issue and protest, this
was the answer he needed for his
subsequent movements.
>> The protest may have been successful in
terms [music] of turnout, but to remain
true to Satyagraha, Gandhi also needed
it to be peaceful.
Only then would it compel the British to
repeal the Rowlatt legislation.
But the dynamic of the protest soon
changed.
It turned violent.
The disturbances had contradicted the
spirit of Satyagraha.
But far from undermining Gandhi, they
would propel him into the center of
Indian politics.
The violence began here at the main
railway station in Delhi.
A large crowd supporting the protest
arrived to persuade the sweet vendors on
the platforms to close their stalls.
The police moved in, arresting some of
the demonstrators, and the crowd
responded by throwing bricks.
The police then opened fire, and five
people were killed.
The violence shocked Gandhi.
But the situation was even worse outside
Delhi.
I'm on my way to the Punjab, the scene
of the most violent disturbances
following the day of protest.
Gandhi attempted to make this same
journey to calm the situation there.
But his train was stopped by the British
authorities, and he was forcibly
removed.
He tried to convince them that he was
traveling to stop unrest, not start it.
Had he got through and succeeded in
halting the violence, the course of
Indian history might have been very
[music] different.
At the heart of the Punjab is the city
of Amritsar, home to the Golden [music]
Temple, the holiest of all Sikh shrines.
The protest in Amritsar [music]
got out of hand. Mobs ran through the
city.
They headed for the banks here in the
main street. One British bank manager
tried to defend himself with his
revolver, but he was murdered by the
crowd. Two others were dragged out into
the street and killed. The British
response was swift. Martial law was
declared, and a general named Reginald
Dyer was given control of the city.
General Dyer arrived at Amritsar
convinced that he had to suppress a
rebellion.
On the morning of the 13th of April, he
issued a proclamation banning all
processions and meetings.
But there were many areas where Dyer
didn't venture, so most people simply
didn't know about the ban.
That afternoon, Dyer heard that a
demonstration was taking place at
Jallianwala Bagh, a park in the center
of the city.
He headed there with 50 Indian troops.
>> Access to the open ground in front was
through just a few of these narrow
alleys. General Dyer and his men would
have walked down here. They would have
left their armored cars back at the
entrance where there was space for them.
And as they came to the end of the
alley, they would immediately have seen
the crowd gathered
>> [music]
>> in front of them.
>> There was a demonstration in the park
against the Rowlatt Act.
But there were also many families
enjoying a religious holiday.
Dyer's troops lined up in front of about
20,000 people.
Without any warning, he gave the order
to shoot.
>> His men fired on where the crowd was
thickest, and again at those who were
trying to flee to make their way to the
few exits. There was a desperate crush
of thousands of people at these exit
points, and you can still see the bullet
holes.
>> The firing lasted for about 10 minutes.
The noise of the guns and the screaming
was so loud that Dyer had trouble making
his ceasefire order heard.
>> One of the few structures here at the
time was a well, which has now been
completely covered over and turned into
a memorial.
In their desperation, people headed for
it,
but many drowned inside, and others were
suffocated under the weight of the
bodies.
About 400 had been killed, and 1,300
people wounded.
Dyer and his troops left the city
without helping the casualties.
He said he didn't want to jeopardize
what he called his victory.
It didn't seem possible that Dyer could
humiliate Indians any further,
but he had a point to prove.
On the day the bank managers were
killed, a British school teacher called
Miss Sherwood had been attacked here and
left for dead until she was rescued by
the father of one of her Indian pupils.
Dyer ordered that anyone walking down
this street who passed what he called
the sacred spot where Miss Sherwood was
assaulted would have to crawl on all
fours.
His soldiers took it a step further and
forced people to crawl on their
stomachs.
Everyone had to crawl, even those who
lived in this street, even those who had
rescued Miss Sherwood.
Although Dyer was eventually made to
leave the army, Indian anger was
inflamed yet further when 26,000 pounds
was raised for him,
a retirement present from a grateful
British public.
And the Rowlatt Act remained law,
another reminder of Britain's treachery.
This year is the 90th anniversary of the
massacre, and amazingly, I've been given
the name of a survivor of Jallianwala
Bagh who's returned from his home in
Australia specially to mark the event.
>> I'm Michelle.
>> Hello, nice to meet
Bapu Singh was a little boy of four when
Dyer arrived to crush his imagined
mutiny.
The massacre transformed his family's
politics and their hopes for India.
>> When
they started firing, people were running
helter-skelter and I was crying and my
grandfather took me
in his arms and he they ran and but we
were lucky actually to escape all that
holocaust.
>> How do you feel when you reflect on the
events of that day?
>> How do I feel? Well, I've got such a
dramatic effect that
I'm just shaken by those feelings and by
those
recollections.
My family
take some part in the freedom movement.
We felt that so many people have
sacrificed their lives on that day, we
were sure that their sacrifices would be
fruitful one day.
>> The massacre was a turning point for the
country. Gandhi's radical philosophy
[music] now seemed to make sense.
In just four years, he'd traveled from
the [music] margins of Indian politics
to its very center.
Even moderates now agreed [music] with
his plans for total non-cooperation with
the British.
The most notable converts were Motilal
Nehru, a leading figure in Congress
politics, and his Harrow-educated son,
Jawaharlal, who would become India's
first Prime Minister.
Historians who've written on the events
of 90 years ago have been struck by the
complex nature of Gandhi's philosophy of
non-violence.
This non-violent campaigner had won
power and influence thanks to the
brutality of the British.
Violence seemed to give Satyagraha the
moral high ground.
And that wasn't the only paradox of
Gandhi's pacifism.
In an extraordinary speech, he declared
that those who died at Jallianwala Bagh
were neither martyrs nor heroes.
Because instead of showing any defiance
to General Dyer, they ran away.
This goes to the heart of Gandhi's
concept of non-violence.
For him, Satyagraha was an act of
bravery, not meekness.
That's why he invented the word because
its meaning, truth force, was stronger
and more powerful than passive
resistance.
The speech was typical Gandhi idealism,
straight out of the ashram.
But it failed to acknowledge the harsh
reality of Amritsar.
The defenseless people in the park that
day probably didn't have a clue about
Satyagraha.
They were just running for their lives.
With increased support [music] in both
Congress and country, in 1920, Gandhi
launched a new campaign of non-violence.
[music]
This time aimed at securing not home
rule, but full independence from
Britain.
He promised a fight to the finish.
But of course, freedom was still 27
years away.
In reality, his so-called fight to the
finish [music] would collapse.
And it would consign Gandhi to the
political wilderness.
This time, for nearly a decade.
And yet, the campaign had all started so
well.
Leading the Satyagraha, Gandhi showed
amazing stamina for a man in his 50s.
For almost a year, he worked tirelessly,
traveling the country in his usual
third-class railway carriages, writing
articles, speaking at meetings,
appealing to Indian lawyers and
policemen to leave their jobs, to
teachers to leave their government-run
schools, and to peasants to stop paying
taxes.
From what I can gather from eyewitness
reports and photographs taken at the
time, Gandhi's public meetings were
fairly simple. He had no microphones at
this point, so few people could actually
hear what he said. One American
journalist said that his voice was
rather thin, and that there were no
elaborate hand gestures. But such was
his charisma and the respect for what
he'd achieved that people were content
simply to see him and be blessed.
The response to the Satyagraha was
heartening. The jails soon began to fill
with workers and peasants prepared to
break the law for the nationalist cause.
There were even stories of people who
were not arrested freely climbing into
prison vans.
The momentum was with Gandhi. His aim of
independence for India suddenly seemed
achievable, his tactics vindicated.
But then, a single incident sent his
political career into a tailspin.
In February 1922 in a town called Chauri
Chaura, a Satyagraha demonstration got
out of control.
A crowd set upon and killed 22 Indian
policemen.
They were shouting, "Victory to Mahatma
Gandhi."
Understandably, he was appalled.
Instead of simply reining in the
rioters, Gandhi suspended the entire
nation-wide campaign.
The decision dismayed many of his
followers.
But Gandhi said that the violence was a
sin against God and that India was not
ready for self-government.
He admitted the decision was politically
unwise, but insisted it was religiously
sound.
The means couldn't be divorced from the
end.
But many of Gandhi's supporters in
Congress were unimpressed.
Jawaharlal Nehru was devastated. He
wanted religion to be kept out of the
independence campaign.
>> [bell]
>> But Gandhi's faith directed all his
actions.
Because he said his political ideas were
derived from his religious beliefs, it
meant he was free to make decisions
according to his inner voice, which he
said was from God.
When you look at his political career,
it means his decisions often appear
erratic and inconsistent.
But he didn't see consistency as a
virtue for a seeker of truth.
Is this a fair assessment?
I met up with Tridip Sarod, one of
India's leading Gandhi scholars, who's
currently writing a major biography.
He believes that India's destiny was
being shaped not just by Gandhi's public
quest for independence, but also by his
private search for God.
>> This desire to see God face-to-face, to
realize the truth that lies within him,
is something which moves him. Uh and I
think that movement begins in South
Africa and continues throughout his
life.
>> How does Gandhi compare with other
political leaders in Congress, for
instance, at that time?
>> No, I think uh Gandhi is very unique uh
in the entire tradition of politics
because he says a nation has to be a
moral entity. Nation is not a political
entity. And that's why when people say
he's the father of the nation, he's the
father of the nation because he
constitutes and creates and constructs
this nation on moral principles.
>> I can see how Gandhi thought that
suspending the campaign in the aftermath
of Chauri Chaura, and therefore
sacrificing short-term political
advantage, would pay off in the end.
The moral virtue of his campaign could
make it unstoppable.
But at the time, it struck his
supporters as the height of folly.
And sure enough, within a month, Gandhi
was under arrest, facing trial, and a
long spell away from politics.
With Gandhi's support ebbing, the
British
>> [music]
>> had seized the initiative.
>> On the evening of Friday, the 10th of
March, 1922, Ahmedabad Superintendent of
Police stopped his car a short distance
from the Ashram and sent word that the
Mahatma should consider himself under
arrest and come out as soon as he was
ready.
As he would have wished, there were no
riots or demonstrations by his
supporters. In fact, the Viceroy, Lord
Reading, would say with satisfaction,
"Not even a dog barked." He wasn't alone
in thinking that Gandhi's political
career was finished.
>> He was charged with writing seditious
articles against His Majesty's
government.
>> Gandhi's trial was to take place here in
Ahmedabad just a week after his arrest.
The judge, Mr. Justice Broomfield,
clearly believed that it wouldn't take
very long. He had just two reminders on
his calendar for that day, play golf and
try Gandhi.
>> Gandhi relished the prospect of a trial.
He knew that he would go to prison and
he used the courtroom as an opportunity
to defend his actions and promote
Satyagraha.
He was sentenced to six years in jail.
Although Gandhi was out of the political
spotlight, international interest grew
in the holy man who'd stood up to the
empire.
Gandhi's growing international
reputation masked a decline in influence
at home.
Indian politics had moved on in the
1920s. Congress, now in moderate hands,
favored working for change with the
British rather than campaigning against
them.
I've come to realize that there was
nothing [music]
inevitable or smooth about Gandhi's rise
to power.
Indeed, when he was finally released
from prison, his views were unchanged.
He was still convinced of the value of
spinning and marching.
But the British saw him as a spent force
and Gandhi himself believed that he
mightn't return [music] to the political
arena.
In 1928, he said, "I have a scheme for
the country's freedom, but my time may
never come."
This marks a real low point in Gandhi's
career.
And it was in danger of plunging even
lower.
Gandhi's vision for a new India was out
of touch with political reality
>> [music]
>> because of another grave development.
A growing rift between Hindus and
Muslims.
This would become the [music] great
fault line of Indian politics.
It's also the moment when my
grandparents' story becomes intertwined
with Gandhi's.
>> So, they had to go to
>> I'm at one of Delhi's hidden treasures,
the summer palace of the last Mughal
emperor, with best-selling author
William Dalrymple.
My family are Muslims originally from
this part of India, and their difficulty
with Gandhi seems to have been that they
didn't feel he represented them. Would
that have been a commonly held view for
Muslims, do you think?
>> I think it was very common, and I think
it grew increasingly common as the 1920s
progressed. Because exactly the sort of
measures that Gandhi took to try and
make Congress more Indian, all had, in
the eyes of many Muslims, a specifically
Hindu character. Many Muslims regarded
him as sort of taking on the
the persona of a of a Hindu holy man.
>> But he was a Hindu, he's entitled to to
adopt that persona as part of him.
>> Yes, but Western lawyers dress is kind
of is
religiously neutral. As soon as he
adopts the the garb of a Hindu peasant,
he immediately becomes something that
Indian Muslims are not.
>> So, the the effect was to exclude
Muslims from from Congress or or from
the from the movement?
>> I think exclude
is is very complex. On one hand, he has
Quranic recitations at his prayer
meetings.
He's got fasting and working for
Hindu-Muslim unity.
On the other hand, while he's all for
Hindu-Muslim unity, he's not perhaps
adequately sensitive to the fears of
Indian Muslims.
>> One of the leading Muslim politicians
was Muhammad Ali Jinnah. The future
founder of Pakistan was a London-trained
lawyer like Gandhi and [music] had
joined the Indian National Congress as a
strong believer in Hindu-Muslim unity.
But William explained how that changed
as Congress came under Gandhi's
influence.
>> The ideologies that that that Gandhi
adopts um
appear to Jinnah to be to be dotty.
Jinnah was thought of himself as an
English gentleman. He liked nicely cut
tweed suits. And a man who likes tweed
suits is not a man who's automatically
going to embrace Gandhi.
>> As the 1920s progressed, Jinnah would in
fact throw his energies behind the
Muslim League, which was fighting to
secure rights for its community.
Jinnah once said Gandhi was in politics
to promote a [music] Hindu revival. But
I think that Gandhi genuinely believed
in the importance of Hindu-Muslim
harmony, illustrated by his many fasts
for unity [music]
and public readings of the Quran.
He simply failed to recognize how he was
being perceived by India's Muslims.
Talking to William also helped me
understand my family's history. My
overriding feeling was relief. The
critical views of Gandhi I'd heard from
them were not untypical.
William helped me see why my
grandparents would have been drawn
towards a separate homeland. The Hindu
overtones of the campaign must have made
them nervous about what an independent
India would be like.
By leaving, they would be safeguarding
their future.
As the 1920s drew to a close and with
Gandhi nearing 60, a betting man might
well have given up on the Mahatma.
In the wilderness for half a decade
[music] and seemingly out of touch with
the realities of Indian politics, Gandhi
himself acknowledged that independence
[music]
seemed a world away.
Fortunately for him, the British once
again showed a skill for crass political
decisions. The result was that once
again, India turned to the Mahatma for a
miracle.
In 1928, the British government
announced that India's future was to be
decided by a commission headed by the MP
Sir John Simon, [music]
but it would be made up entirely of
British parliamentarians.
To the fury of Congress, Indians would
not be allowed to shape [music] their
own destiny.
They turned to Gandhi to organize a mass
protest [music] against British rule.
He rose to the challenge with possibly
the greatest political campaign of the
20th century. [music]
It would impress not only Congress,
but the whole world.
All those who thought that Gandhi was a
spent force were in for a surprise. His
tactic was simple. He would walk 240
miles from the Ashram to the sea. There
he would collect salt from a beach, boil
it and purify it. This was how the
Mahatma planned to dislodge the British
from India.
Gandhi's [music] political allies took
some convincing that this was the right
issue. Even Nehru, now president of
Congress, was unimpressed, unable to see
what common salt [music] had to do with
a national struggle.
But for Gandhi, it was clear the British
tax on salt was immoral as it penalized
[music]
the poor.
I asked Narayan Desai, who lived on the
Ashram at the time, to take me on the
salt march route.
I want to find out what made this
campaign so successful.
Of course, Gandhi would not approve of
the fact that we're traveling
in a car.
>> I have traveled in a car with Gandhi and
he had never disapproved of it.
>> As dawn broke on the morning of the 12th
of March, Gandhi set off from the Ashram
followed [music] by 78 carefully
selected marchers.
A few days out from the Ashram, Gandhi
passed close to this village.
Narayan shows me a thriving project
inspired by Gandhi's belief in
self-sufficiency.
It proves that while his campaigns were
sometimes derided as old-fashioned,
history shows that his instincts were
often spot on.
>> I'm Michelle.
>> Hello, very nice
>> Ela Bhatt is known throughout India as
the founder of SEWA, a trade union
that's transformed the lives of
thousands of women.
The union owes its origins to Gandhi's
1917 campaign in support of striking
textile workers, a campaign ignored by
Congress.
In this village, the skills of spinning
and weaving have been revived to give
the women regular employment.
>> So, this what what they're actually
producing is khadi, exactly what Gandhi
taught taught campaigns to to encourage
people to wear.
>> This is yeah, very much a khadi cloth.
>> That's really beautiful.
>> The reason that Gandhi was so concerned
for the poor is the same reason that
motivates Ela.
>> I think poverty is unacceptable.
It is man-made. It it is not given by
God.
And it has to be removed.
Because poverty is an ongoing
violence.
Uh it strips off the people from their
dignity. So, I saw this as injustice.
>> So, they're both wearing saris that that
they made themselves here.
>> themselves.
>> On the very route of Gandhi's salt march
of eight decades ago, his spirit can be
found in villages like this.
These women have the self-sufficiency
and self-respect that he so wished for
the whole of India.
Gandhi [music] was extraordinarily fit
for a 61-year-old who ate little more
than nuts and fruit. Obsessively
punctual, he constantly consulted the
pocket watch that hung from his waist,
and he expected his marchers to be
equally disciplined.
We've been told of a location that has
barely changed since the marchers stayed
there 80 years ago.
This is a school in the village of
Borsad.
>> I'll just introduce you to Narayan Bhai.
>> We're met by the school principal, who
shows us around.
In this classroom, the desks were
removed so that Gandhi could spend the
night here.
But before he slept, he spoke to a crowd
of over a thousand people from this
balcony, declaring that to be loyal to
the British Empire was a sin.
He addressed the crowd here.
So, the whole of Borsad came to hear him
speak.
It's a special moment to be able to
stand here and imagine the excitement of
that day when the Mahatma came to this
small school.
The principal is Asnarayan to speak to
one of her classes about his life with
Gandhi.
But, despite their school's history, his
audience is rather shy and reluctant.
>> Gandhi wasn't a politician.
Bapu, or a Mahatma, he was our friend.
What sort of friend?
We all used to bathe in the Sabarmati
River
and splash water in his face.
And he used to splash water in ours.
That's the type of friends we were.
>> As Narayan spoke, it was amazing to
watch these girls become transfixed as
he brought Gandhi to life.
>> I could type, so I used to type his
letters.
Have you heard of Hitler? Yes?
Gandhi wrote a letter to Hitler saying,
"If you wish, you can stop the fighting
in the world."
I typed that letter.
When Bapu died,
I was 24 years old.
He once gave me a book
and he had written in it,
"The hopes I have for you,
you must fulfill them."
So, I've spent 60 years wondering
what hopes Gandhi had for me.
You've got another 60 years to think
about what hopes Bapu has for you.
>> When you are young.
>> [music]
>> As our day on the salt march ends,
Narayan and I rest under a mango tree in
the village of Vasna. The same tree that
Gandhi himself rested under all those
years ago.
Do you wish that you had been old enough
to go on the salt march with Gandhi?
>> Uh not today. At that time probably.
Because I spent 10 years with him.
Almost all 24 hours of the day.
>> You didn't need to go on a salt march to
be close to Gandhi. [music]
>> No, because all the time I was marching
along with him.
>> On the 5th of April, a month after
leaving the Ashram, the marchers reached
the outskirts of their destination,
Dandi, a small village on the [music]
Gujarati coast.
There were already scores of journalists
waiting to see the final act of this
remarkable drama. [music]
Showing a very modern flair for the
sound bite, [music]
Gandhi scribbled a note to them.
I want world sympathy in this battle of
right against might.
And he showed an equally modern flair
for the media gesture.
The following morning, after bathing in
the sea, Gandhi walked back to the
beach. He scooped up some salt
and showed it to the crowd. "With this,"
he said, "I'm shaking the foundations of
the British Empire."
The marchers [music] then headed into
the sea with pots and pans, boiled the
water, and made their own illegal salt.
That was [music] provocation enough.
But with the world press watching,
Gandhi seized the advantage.
Gandhi decided that the nearby
commercial salt works at Tarasana,
[music]
still in use today, would be the target
for a Satyagraha protest.
He wrote to Lord Irwin saying that
unless the salt tax [music] was removed,
he and his marchers would demand
possession of the salt works.
>> [music]
>> He had just finished the letter when he
was arrested at midnight by 30 [music]
armed policemen.
With Gandhi on his way to a Bombay jail,
it was his wife Kasturba who blessed the
marchers [music] as they set off for
Tarasana.
This time, there [music] was no
undefended beach.
Waiting for them were 400 Indian
policemen, some with rifles, [music]
all with steel-tipped sticks called
lathis.
Some journalists were already there,
warned of what might happen next.
One of the correspondents watching was
an American journalist called Webb
Miller. This is his account of what
happened next.
In complete silence, the Gandhi men drew
up and halted a hundred yards from the
stockade.
Suddenly, at a word of command, scores
of native police rushed upon the
advancing marchers and [music] rained
blows on their heads with their
steel-shod lathis.
Not one of the marchers even raised an
arm to fend off the blows.
They went down [music] like tenpins.
From where I stood, I heard the
sickening whacks of the clubs on
unprotected skulls.
In two or three minutes, the ground was
quilted with bodies.
Although everyone knew that within a few
minutes he would [music] be beaten down,
perhaps killed, I could detect no signs
of wavering or fear.
The police rushed out [music] and
methodically and mechanically beat down
the second column.
There was no fight, no struggle.
The marchers simply [music] walked
forward
until struck down.
Webb Miller counted two dead and 320
injured.
His report was printed in a thousand
newspapers around the world.
For me, this bloody episode has helped
clarify my thoughts about Gandhi and his
non-violent campaigns.
I wonder, was this act the bravery that
Gandhi so admired and had been looking
for in his own followers? The manliness
that he thought was lacking in Amritsar?
The fearlessness that he wanted from the
ashram?
Was this truth force in action?
Certainly, the followers of Satyagraha
here showed unbelievable courage. You
would hope that their injuries weren't
in vain.
So, what was achieved by the salt march
and the violent confrontation [music] at
Dharasana?
In the eyes of the world, Britain had
suffered a severe blow to its moral
authority, just as Gandhi [music] had
hoped it would.
Within a year, Gandhi would be out of
prison and embraced [music] by adorning
followers
and invited by Lord Irwin to hold talks
in the grandeur of Imperial Delhi.
In a defiant [music] touch, Gandhi took
some illegal salt with him and used it
in front of the Viceroy.
>> [music]
>> But what they discussed was not as
important as the symbolism of those
talks.
For 3 weeks, the former prisoner was
treated as an equal [music]
by the Viceroy of India.
Gandhi's rise to power was far from
straightforward.
Yet he dominates the 1920s.
It's the charisma and determination he
shows on the salt march that propels him
and India into the next [music] decade.
After the march, Nehru had congratulated
Gandhi on the new India you've created
by your magic touch.
In 15 years, Gandhi had launched a mass
movement from almost nothing and
transformed Congress. But it was too
early to talk of a new India. Gandhi and
Nehru would now not only have to battle
the British, but also those the Mahatma
had alienated, notably Jinnah and the
Muslim League. Jinnah, Nehru, and
Gandhi, these three London-trained
lawyers would fight for the destiny of
India. The seeds of partition had been
sown.
>> [music]
>> On the final stage of my journey, Gandhi
takes his fight to the heart of the
empire.
And I discover how my family's lives
were changed [music] forever by Gandhi's
greatest triumph and his greatest
disappointment.